number eight on my list is getting good
sleep now you don't have to be perfect
here but one of the things we know
happens with really bad sleep even on a
single day is people tend to seek out
more total calories and it makes sense
you're tired you feel like you're in a
low energy State you're going to want to
get more energy that's exactly what your
body is doing and is a natural response
this has been shown extensively in the
literature under acute fatigue from lack
of sleep people will search out more
total calories and I'll also search out
food items that tend to be higher energy
density you can think about these as
junk Foods if you'd like I know
personally I search after carbohydrates
I don't know why but I really want more
bread I really not that the bread is bad
for you but I really want carbohydrates
when I'm fatigued again intuitively it
actually makes a ton of sense this is
the primary and fastest energy source
for your body but that one hits me very
directly so I know that's something I
have to watch out for and has been shown
multiple times most people are like that
and the physiology makes intuitive sense
so if you're wanting to then quote
unquote speed up your
metabolism ensuring you're not in a spot
repeatedly where sleep is bad therefore
it's not that your metabolic rate has
changed but you're going to make worse
food choices and so your total energy
intake is higher which means your intake
versus energy out that balance is off
which is is then going to lead to
eventual body composition changes so
there's more to say on that but that's
if you're a little bit confused on why
that is on my list it's not necessarily
that sleep will enhance your metabolism
but bad sleep can have a number of
negative impacts and one of them being
behavioral changes specifically with
food and calorie intake one thing that
will suppress acutely and chronically as
we'll talk about later your total daily
energy expenditure and specifically RMR
is really bad sleep neat specifically
will go down in the presence of poor
sleep acute and chronic the one night of
bad sleep is probably not a big deal but
magnifi over time will make a huge
impact so your neat is going to go down
your drive for Worse food choices and
more food overall will increase energy
expenditure might also go down you know
it's harder to work out you're not going
to take the walks you're not you're more
likely to skip your training sessions or
condense them or just get through it
when you've had a bad night of sleep and
you also are going to potentially see
red reductions in resting metabolic rate
and so for me personally what I do when
I have a bad night of sleep and it
happens I have kids and I travel and all
kinds of things happen three things I do
to mitigate this damage number one what
I've already talked about I will double
triple down as much as I can on protein
basically I'm trying to crowd out other
Foods so I know I just really want to go
for Burgers and Fries and stuff like
that and I know it's cuz I slept for 3
hours night before I'm going to smash a
double scoop of protein I'm just going
to keep it really really really high I
still might go get those foods but I
just don't have the physical space in my
stomach anymore I get full of course
occasionally I'm a person I'll just go
have the burgers and fries I'm not
neurotic about it but if this stuff
happens somewhat regularly you can't
always fall into that trap at some point
you need to make sure you don't do that
willpower is one way but personally I
just make sure I'm smashing protein
throughout the day to reduce that risk
second thing I do is I make sure I hit
all that lowlevel energy expenditure
stuff so maybe I don't have it in me to
do my interval training or my assault
bike or run my Hills or whatever but
I'll make sure I walk let's move around
let's get three or four of those
10-minute walks in no matter how tired
and sleepy I am or sick for the most
part you can probably get yourself to
walk those couple hundred calories are
going to add up especially again if this
happens frequently uh sauna is another
good one sauna is not a replacement for
exercise
but hey you can a lot of times convince
yourself to take a hot bath or a sauna
and get something out of the day third
thing I do and this is going to stun
people but take a nap go ahead and
actually just sleep you could suffer all
throughout the day making worse choices
and skipping your workout or maybe that
30 60 or 90 minute nap while you're
going to feel like you're not working
that time because you're not if it
substantially enhances the quality of
the next 10 hours of your day sneaking
in a little bit of may change everything
and is a good thing to do again when you
magnify this stuff over time to the real
shabam here and that's resting metabolic
ratee this is the one we're after and
the only one that really matters in
terms of me officially saying yes we
have boosted your metabolism in a way
that you care about and will matter got
a handful of ways to do that and the
very first one is sleep we talked about
this with a cute but the impacts of
sleep are far better explained from The
Chronic
side enormous amounts of data here and
much of it is very recent in fact we had
very little understanding of the
metabolic ties between sleep and
Metabolism until the last really 10
years or so now the relationship between
sleep and metabolism is bidirectional we
talked about bad sleep changing
metabolism a second ago but it goes the
opposite direction as well a bunch of
research I could pull up here but a
couple of ones that I've found most
interesting that I wanted to highlight
one study in particular that came out of
the University of Chicago a number of
years ago looked at 10 overweight
individuals and they put them on a
14-day caloric restriction protocol and
one of the times they went through the
protocol they slept eight and 1 half
hours the other time they went through
the protocol they slept 5 and 1 half
hours so again University controlled
calories in both situations the only
variable that changed was three hours of
sleep so now we're not even talking
about the impact of bad nutritional
choices this is simply even if calories
are matched what happens when you sleep
more right now the Sleep curtailment
group the sleep that the group that
slept for five and a half hours had a
reduction in fat loss by
55% in absolute terms you're talking
about the difference between like 1.4
kilos versus 6 kilos so almost a full
kilogram difference in fat loss that
favored the group who slept more the
same thing basically happened in terms
of muscle mass uh you can't directly
measure it in the study but it's called
fat-free body mass and just think of it
like muscle mass and this was about a
60% difference so absolute terms you're
talking about 1.5 kilos versus 2.4 kilos
so almost a full kilogram or about 2 lbs
of lean muscle difference this is
substantial remember this is 14 days
that's it and all they Chang was sleep
and we see pronounced increases in fat
and reduction in muscle growth with just
this variable change right so what you
can see there is additional stuff that
they looked at actually fat oxidation um
satiety I think as well was in there but
really problematic uh things going on
when you sleep
poorly that relationship uh if I had to
summarize the literature you're going to
see like a 10 to 60% increased
likelihood of a obesity with bad sleep
so there's a chronic effect here that is
very very real one more time it's
bidirectional so we see what I'm meaning
there is if you are overweight you're
probably going to have worse sleep but
worse sleep is actually going to cause
overweight so the cause goes both
directions there really nice paper came
out pretty recently it'll be up in the
show notes you can check it out
specifically on the relationship between
obesity and sleep and how it goes both
directions you can see those details and
that but another thing that is that has
been identified in the literature there
is the direct relationship between
muscle mass and sleep and it goes the
way that you would predict not only does
more fat often times equal worse sleep
but more muscle oftentimes equals better
sleep so two independent things
happening there not enough
muscle bad too much fat bad there's a
relationship as well there but they are
separate and we need to acknowledge that
so it's not only important to make sure
we're we not overfat but that we have
muscle as well this is actually an area
that's getting a lot of scientific
attention right now that people don't
necessarily realize and that is normal
weight
obesity you heard that right normal
weight obesity so people whose total
body weight is not exceptionally high
but their body fat percentage is really
high probably not kindly put but you may
know this more cloy as skinny fat the
more proper term is again normal weight
obesity but this is an area again
scientifically that's getting a lot of
attention right now because of
acknowledgement of things like that it's
not necessarily just about body weight
but the quality of that body weight
matters a ton more research on this
chronic tie between resting metabolic
rate and bad sleep very very famous
study in the field called The Sleep
heart health study um this was
self-reported sleep folks that
self-reported less than five hours of
sleep per night had and this is going to
stun you here this was associated with a
250 51% increase in their Hazard ratio
of developing type 2 diabetes Now type
two diabetes and obesity are not the
same thing but obviously there's a
strong relationship there what we're
seeing here is just general metabolic
dysfunction with bad sleep similar
things have been done with impaired
insulin signaling specifically in atpo
cells those your fat cells in folks who
sleep five and a half hours versus eight
and a half hours so we're seeing this in
a lot of different forms and fashion in
fact one of the papers and I'm going to
quote it directly here because it's so
powerful uh specifically said that quote
from a clinical standpoint our study
provides additional evidence that
insufficient sleep May contribute to the
development of or exacerbate metabolic
disorders I can tell you in my coaching
experience it is really really hard to
manage body composition and thus
metabolic rate and somebody who is truly
chronically sleeping really poorly it is
tough you got to fix that sleep or at
least improve it before you expect major
changes in body composition one night of
sleep not a big deal bad nights of sleep
though you're probably going to expect a
reduced resting metabolic rate which is
why it's in our chronic section and a
big big big hammer to swing if you
enjoyed this clip you can watch the full
episode by clicking here